<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<corpus>
  <article id="a160" issue="120" name="Thinking by feeling" lang="en">
    <div class="title">Thinking by feeling</div>
    <div class="date">07/03/2019</div>
    <div class="author">Yvonne Vahlensieck</div>
    <div class="abstract">Subjective feelings are at home in all regions of the brain, and visualisation processes can now make them accessible to scientists. Researchers want to devise new therapies for depression, and achieve a greater understanding of economic decisions.
</div>
    <div>Objective methods can even measure subjective things – like emotions. | Image: Fred Merz</div>
    <div>Joy, anger, fear, surprise, disgust and sadness – these are feelings we all know. But just twenty years ago, psychologists were still investigating them primarily by interviewing test subjects and monitoring their physical reactions – their heartbeat, respiratory rate and facial expressions.</div>
    <div>Emotion research has come a long way since then. Using new methods such as functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI), neuroscientists can now analyse what happens in the brain when they awaken different emotions in their test subjects. To this end, they might show them photographs of happy or sad faces, let them smell chocolate or play them clips of horror films. Using fMRI, they can then measure the blood flow in the brain and thereby determine which regions of the brain have been activated.</div>
    <div>“In this way, we can now develop objective measuring methods for mechanisms that are in themselves subjective”, says David Sander, the director of the Swiss Center for Affective Sciences (SCAS). “That’s one of the reasons why visualisation methods in the brain are so fascinating”. The SCAS is based at the University of Geneva and grew out of the National Centre of Competence in Research ‘Affective Sciences – Emotions in Individual Behaviour and Social Processes’ (see the box ‘Emotions from all sides now’). Of course, the researchers can’t actually look at the emotions in the brain, but they can observe how different emotional processes activate different regions of the brain in different ways. “And that’s incredibly useful”, says Sander.</div>
    <div>The whole brain feels it</div>
    <div>The researchers have also been scrutinising several prevailing theories in emotion research. For example, the amygdala, an almond-shaped structure in the centre of the brain, was long regarded as the seat of fear. These new studies have confirmed its role in this, but they have also shown that the amygdala is important for processing many other emotions too, both positive and negative. “We have since come to believe that the amygdala in general helps us in the subjective evaluation of how important a situation is”, says Sander. For this reason, it is a key structure for triggering and regulating emotions in general, far beyond mere fear.</div>
    <div>It was also surprising for them to learn that emotions don’t just influence the more supposedly ‘primitive’ regions of the brain. “We used to think that reason and the emotions stood in opposition to each other”, says Sander. “But we know now that regions of the brain previously believed to be responsible only for higher cognitive functions can be greatly influenced by emotions”. This is also something positive, because emotions help us to make many personal decisions. To Sander, there is no doubt about it: “Emotions and cognition don’t in any way exist in opposition to each other”.</div>
    <div>Emotions on the financial markets</div>
    <div>One of these higher cognitive functions is the ability to make good decisions. Researchers in neuroeconomics are particularly interested in what happens in the brain during the decision-making process. This means that emotion research is also beginning to make societal interrelations more comprehensible.</div>
    <div>“Economists have observed that when people make decisions entailing risk, they don’t act according to the predictions of their financial models. In other words, from a business standpoint, they act irrationally”, says Kerstin Preuschoff, a professor of neureoeconomics at the University of Geneva. “But emotion research has now proven that this behaviour isn’t so incomprehensible after all, because emotions play an important role in decision making”. Preuschoff was able to use fMRI studies to demonstrate that concepts from the world of finance, such as inherent risk and expected value, are reflected in specific regions of the brain. “Our research started on a very small scale, looking at decisions made by individuals, but now we are dealing with highly complex decision-making processes on the financial markets”, says Preuschoff.</div>
    <div>Ultimately, the goal of neuroeconomics, she says, is to incorporate these new components into calculations for financial models. She admits that this research is still in its early stages. “But soon we will probably be able to read brain signals to determine the results of investment decisions”.</div>
    <div>Virtual reality is more real</div>
    <div>To get that far, the technology they use to read the brain’s emotions will have to be further improved. “Most researchers still use indirect methods to trigger emotions”, says the neuroscientist Patrik Vuilleumier of the SCAS. For example, looking at a happy face activates certain regions of the brain, but without necessarily triggering a real emotion of happiness.</div>
    <div>This is why Vuilleumier is developing a new procedure that will use VR goggles to put his test subjects in a virtual world where they can solve tasks and survive assorted adventures. In Vuilleumier’s opinion, this immersion will enable him to trigger emotions that are almost natural. Using statistical methods and fMRI analyses, he will then be able to evaluate which factors in the virtual scenarios trigger what activity in the brain.</div>
    <div>Psychologists are meanwhile also making use of the fact that virtual experiences can provide direct access to the world of emotions. For example, the Department of Cognitive Neuroscience at the University of Basel has been testing smartphone apps that use virtual or augmented reality to treat spider phobia and vertigo. The advantage of this is that the people affected are confronted realistically with their fears, but nevertheless always have their situation under control.</div>
    <div>Controlling your own emotions</div>
    <div>Emotion research also offers new perspectives for treating mental illness, because many disorders involve regions of the brain that help to process emotions. For example, in many depressives there is diminished feedback between cognitive brain areas and the emotion-processing amygdala. “We have recently made quite a lot of progress, and can now better understand how disruptions in emotion processing are connected to psychiatric illnesses”, says the neuroscientist Frank Scharnowski. “But translating this new knowledge into new brain-based therapies is going to be a huge leap”.</div>
    <div>Scharnowski is investigating just such an innovative therapeutic approach – so-called neurofeedback – in research projects at the Psychiatric University Hospital Zurich and at the University of Vienna. In neurofeedback training, people learn to control quite specific areas of the brain. To this end, their brain activity is constantly monitored by means of fMRI. If test subjects succeed in regulating the desired area of the brain – such as the amygdala – then they get positive feedback. Scharnowski says that most healthy people are able to learn this method in just a few sessions, and that patients suffering from depression or anxiety disorders can benefit from it.</div>
    <div>Scharnowski’s results prove that psychiatric patients aren’t simply at the mercy of their emotions, but that opportunities exist for them to learn to control them. In normal cases, however, this isn’t even necessary, because emotions make a valuable contribution to our thoughts and actions. Sander agrees: “Of course, emotions sometimes prevent us from making good decisions. But there are also situations where emotions are necessary for us to make the best ones”.</div>
  </article>
  <article id="a161" issue="120" name="Academia aims to reduce its own CO2 emissions" lang="en">
    <div class="title">Academia aims to reduce its own CO2 emissions</div>
    <div class="date">07/03/2019</div>
    <div class="author">Marcel Falk</div>
    <div class="abstract">Researchers fly all over the world to take part in conferences and exchange ideas face-to-face. And they often do so without thinking about the impact on our climate. But if the oncologist Daniel Helbling has his way, that will soon change. We look at three initiatives from scientists who are keen to improve the sustainability of their own disciplines. 
</div>
    <div>Marco Mazzotti | Illustration: 1kilo</div>
    <div>“If we are really going to change things, then we first have to change our culture”, says Marco Mazzotti from the Department of Mechanical and Process Engineering at ETH Zurich. Back in 2017, ETH instructed all its departments to set goals for reducing greenhouse gases, and to state how these were to be achieved. Right from the start, Mazzotti got his students and postdocs involved. And the measures decided upon also put his students centre-stage. Financed by a CO2 levy on flights, students will be able to carry out concrete projects from 2019 onwards with the aim of pursuing these sustainability goals. “In this manner, hundreds of students each year can think about these problems and gather experience in how science can be made more sustainable”, says Mazzotti.</div>
    <div>Daniel Helbling | Illustration: 1kilo</div>
    <div>Every year, over 40,000 oncologists fly to the five-day conference of the American Society of Clinical Oncology. But some specialists from Switzerland prefer to travel instead to the quiet village of Flüeli-Ranft in the canton of Obwalden. They come together in an art nouveau hotel for three days at the same time that the conference takes place in the USA. A programme committee and numerous scouts check out the 4,000-5,000 papers scheduled for the US conference in advance, and choose those that seem the most relevant for Switzerland. “This saves a huge amount of time for our participants”, says Daniel Helbling from the OnkoZentrum in Zurich, one of the initiators of the Swiss meeting. The Swiss doctors gathered in Flüeli watch their chosen lectures by video, one day after they are given in the USA. They discuss them amongst themselves, but also engage with the speakers in the USA by means of a video link. “We save time, money and some 133 tonnes of CO2 every year”, says Helbling. “When I used to attend these conferences, I was exhausted afterwards, and simply knocked out by the huge number papers on offer. These days, I’m well-informed, but feel refreshed”.</div>
    <div>Gisou van der Goot | Illustration: 1kilo</div>
    <div>Gisou van der Goot is Dean of the Faculty of Life Sciences at EPFL. Shocked by the amount of CO2 emissions from flights by members of her Faculty, she developed an ambitious plan to halve their emissions. “We are encouraging our assistant professors to attend just three international conferences a year”, she says. Exchanging ideas with fellow scientists remains important, of course, and to this end van der Goot intends setting up a first-class infrastructure for videoconferencing, and wants to organise regional and national hubs during international conferences. EPFL management is still working to develop the best combination of measures. “We fell like trendsetters”, says van der Goot.</div>
    <div>Researchers fly a lot – even those whose field is climate change. But reducing their greenhouse emissions by some 40 percent wouldn’t even mean less travelling. All they have to do is take the train instead. And to fly economy class when they absolutely have to take the plane. Statistics released by ETH Zurich and EPFL offer convincing proof that this works.</div>
    <div>ETH Zurich has been mobilising. All its departments and its administrative staff have had to state how they intend to reduce their greenhouse gas emissions. The result is a multitude of ideas, with one goal: a reduction in emissions of 11 percent per capita by 2025. These measures were implemented in January 2019. We offer a selection of the ideas here.</div>
    <div>Reassessing ETH rules on climate suitability</div>
    <div>Ideas for combatting greenhouse gases. | Illustration: 1kilo</div>
    <div>Reto Knutti, a climate researcher at ETH Zurich, is focusing his activity on a national level and never takes intercontinental flights just for one-day events. We here interview him about the difficulties of being environmentally conscious as a researcher.</div>
    <div>Reto Knutti is a researcher at ETH Zurich and is the chairman of ProClim, the Forum for Climate and Global Change of the Swiss Academy of Sciences. | Illustration: 1kilo</div>
    <div>ETH Zurich wants to reduce its greenhouse gas emissions by 11 percent by the year 2025. Is that enough?</div>
    <div>No, but it’s an important initial step. In Switzerland, we’re taking more and more flights. But we’re setting a different trend at ETH Zurich.</div>
    <div>But the next 89 percent are going to be more difficult, aren’t they?</div>
    <div>Not necessarily. We need to bring about a profound shift. Whoever wants to be regarded as a top-class researcher has to travel internationally. And when choosing conferences to attend, organising research partners or setting up field studies, distance no longer matters today. Changing this state of affairs will be the most difficult task. But we’re currently engaged in discussions about it.</div>
    <div>Is global science possible without air travel?</div>
    <div>It’s possible with far fewer flights than we take at present. And in individual cases, a researcher indeed has to be on the spot – such as when setting up new partnerships.</div>
    <div>What do researchers and institutions risk if they rush ahead with these restrictive measures?</div>
    <div>It’s difficult for younger researchers, because they first have to establish themselves on the scene. So we can’t just make demands; we have to change the evaluation criteria. Ecologically responsible behaviour mustn’t become an impediment to anyone’s career, or to achieving excellence in academia. For institutions, this turnaround also has advantages. The actual costs of taking lots of flights are greatly underestimated. I’m thinking here of the time invested, then jetlag, and the impact on one’s family.</div>
    <div>Is it the duty of science to do something about it?</div>
    <div>Sure. When you’re dealing with a global problem such as climate change, you can’t afford to allow any freeloaders. Everyone has to play a part, not just researchers. After all, the average Swiss citizen flies more miles per capita than any ETH scientist undertakes for his research.</div>
    <div>And what’s your own stance regarding flights?</div>
    <div>These days, I’m more active on a national level, and I’m finding projects here that are just as relevant as anything abroad. I fly as little as absolutely possible, never business class, and I never take an intercontinental flight for any event that lasts just a day.</div>
  </article>
  <article id="a162" issue="120" name="You can’t quote feelings" lang="en">
    <div class="title">You can’t quote feelings</div>
    <div class="date">07/03/2019</div>
    <div class="author">Franca Siegfried</div>
    <div class="abstract">They live for their work, and impact factor is vital to them – but researchers rarely talk about feelings at their workplace. Their emotions aren’t mentioned in any of their publications. So we’ve asked four researchers to tell us about their emotional moments. 
</div>
    <div>Illustration: Irene Sackmann</div>
    <div>Excited</div>
    <div>Federica Rossi (41), Archivio del Moderno at Università della Svizzera italiana</div>
    <div>“When I’m in an archive, I lose all sense of time. It’s quiet in the darkened room – there’s no telephone, and hardly any people. My research is something intimate. I’m looking for the stories of people who built up Moscow in just five years. When Napoleon occupied the city in 1812, a fire destroyed three-quarters of all its buildings. It is a little-known fact that the reconstruction of the city was especially dominated by architects from the canton of Ticino. I feel rather like a Sherlock Holmes for the past. It’s tantalising and exciting to search for the date and the signature in a new document, or to read letters from aristocrats to the Ticino architect Domenico Gilardi. We’re in the second year of the project, and these long-dead people are becoming my friends. I’m familiar with them, they have a face, even a character. Sometimes, Russian colleagues help me in my archival research. Who’s going to find out first whether a document is the original or a copy? We concentrate on the document and submerge ourselves in the flow of it – it’s an exhilarating feeling that then unites us”.</div>
    <div>Illustration: Irene Sackmann</div>
    <div>Sad</div>
    <div>Patrick Michel (36), Institute of Archaeology and Antiquity Sciences of the University of Lausanne</div>
    <div>“When Islamic State demolished the Baalshamin temple in Palmyra, Syria, in August 2015, it was a real shock. As a child, I’d experienced the war in Lebanon and I remember the cities that were destroyed. Now we’re talking about an archaeological site. I cried. I felt a deep disgust, but also partly a cue: I realised that in the archives at the University of Lausanne there was something that would allow us to bring the monument back to life. The data was collected in the 1950s by the Swiss archaeologist Paul Collart. There was no way for us to keep it under lock and key. There was a duty to memory, to science and to humanity.</div>
    <div>Our 3D modelling shows the evolution of the site over more than a thousand years, from 200 BC to 1200 AD. Our work was first revealed to the public at an exhibition, from which visitors have been leaving in tears. But most of all, we created this project with Syrians in mind, especially children who’ve been born in refugee camps, so that they can keep in touch with their cultural heritage. Participating in this virtual reconstruction has given me hope and affords immense meaning to my work”.</div>
    <div>Illustration: Irene Sackmann</div>
    <div>Annoyed</div>
    <div>Martin Fussenegger (50), Department of Biosystems Science and Engineering, ETH Zurich</div>
    <div>“You can’t plan your research. Why not? Because we can’t look into the future. Today, we’re constrained by administration. First I have to construct a hypothesis, then I write a plan. As soon as the project is given the go-ahead and we’ve got the money, I can begin to research. After that, I am constantly writing reports for monitoring purposes, to prove whether or not I’m spending the money properly. If I discover something interesting that doesn’t fit my assigned project, I have to write a new hypothesis and a new application – everything is regulated. Administration costs a lot of money and time. And that’s time away from our research. What annoys me even more is the belief that there’s a perfect system that doesn’t allow for mistakes. But as biologists we know that every system comprises between five and ten percent mistakes. That’s how it stays flexible. So my appeal to the world of the universities is for them to acknowledge that regulation and creativity are not very compatible!”</div>
    <div>Illustration: Irene Sackmann</div>
    <div>Happy</div>
    <div>Nadine Ringgenberg (33), Federal Food Safety and Veterinary Office FSVO</div>
    <div>“I find it very satisfying to find out how ramps, perches and nests for laying hens can be organised optimally so that the animals have as happy a life as possible. I really enjoy it every time we’re able to translate our research results into practice, and it motivates me. Because I’m really concerned about the wellbeing of the animals. There was a wonderful moment last autumn when we were able to inaugurate the new experimental pen for poultry and rabbits in Zollikofen. I was grateful when after a year of building work, the first chickens were able to enter it. The hygienic conditions, the ventilation and the infrastructure have all been greatly improved. Now I hope that we will be able to improve the lives of thousands of chickens in Switzerland.</div>
  </article>
  <article id="a163" issue="120" name="Sun, snow and avalanches" lang="en">
    <div class="title">Sun, snow and avalanches</div>
    <div class="date">07/03/2019</div>
    <div class="author">Alexandra Bröhm</div>
    <div class="abstract">Although it’s extremely rare for avalanches to reach populated areas in Switzerland, they are responsible for several deaths off-piste every winter.
</div>
    <div>Once or twice a week, Bastian Bergfeld goes on a ski tour. The avalanche researcher (here in the red jacket) throws his acceleration sensors into the snow in front of him, in order to measure how quickly fractures in the snow layers spread out. | Image: Alec van Herwijnen, SLF.</div>
    <div>Early this year, a wall of snow stormed into the Hotel Säntis on the Schwägalp. Although it’s extremely rare for avalanches to reach populated areas in Switzerland, they are responsible for several deaths off-piste every winter. Bastian Bergfeld from the Institute for Snow and Avalanche Research SLF in Davos regularly ventures out onto the slopes in his quest to improve the science of avalanche prognosis.</div>
    <div>Bastian Bergfeld studies the snow profile to determine the stability of the different layers. | Image: Stephanie Mayer, SLF</div>
    <div>Bastian Bergfeld studied physics at the Ludwig-Maximilian University in Munich. He came across the field of avalanche studies while working on his Master’s degree, and was able to continue his research at the Institute for Snow and Avalanche Research SLF in Davos. He is currently writing his doctoral thesis about how avalanches are formed and how they can be prevented.</div>
    <div>“Every ski tourer fears that sound. ‘Boom’, but it can be loud or soft, long or short. Regardless of how it sounds, it means danger. It means that a weak layer has broken under the snow slab you’re standing on. On steep ground, it could trigger a slab avalanche. One focus of my research here at the SLF is finding out why and when it goes ‘boom’. Ninety percent of avalanche accidents are the result of slab avalanches set off by people practising sport. It’s our goal to keep improving avalanche prognoses. One of the things we’re investigating is how the fracture spreads in the weak layer, and how fast. It happens at a crazy speed – sometimes at over 100 kilometres an hour.</div>
    <div>“This means that once or twice a week, I have to take the first funicular of the morning up the Schatzalp, above Davos. That doesn’t bother me, I’m an early riser anyway. We’re equipped like ski tourers. Besides our standard safety equipment, such as avalanche transceivers, spades and probes, the Institute also provides us with airbag rucksacks. After all, we’ve got to go where avalanches happen. From the mountain station of the funicular, we ski up towards the Strelapass into the Steintälli. The conditions for our research are good there. We naturally don’t go to the steep slopes. We seek out places where we can trigger a fracture in the weak layer without getting into danger ourselves – in other words, we stay on flat terrain.</div>
    <div>“Avalanches can be devastating, but luckily they’re also relatively rare events. This also makes them more difficult to investigate. There are many factors that play a role in each instance. There’s the composition of the snow cover, the wind, the temperature, the terrain. So we need a lot of patience in our work. In order to measure the speed at which the fracture spreads, we’ve developed eight acceleration sensors, each about as big as your fist. We ski in a line and throw them in a big arc in front of us, always several metres apart. They’re attached to a long strap so we can find them later in the snow. If we trigger a fracture, then these sensors can help us calculate how fast it spreads.</div>
    <div>“I think many ski tourers have a false sense of security. They might have only narrowly avoided triggering an avalanche numerous times, but aren’t aware of it. You only notice it when it’s too late, because you don’t see what’s happening under the visible snow slab. You can’t know if the slab is already weak and on the verge of collapsing. As for me, I’m a passionate ski tourer, but I think it’s my research that has made me more careful. Today, I know just how many unknowns there are. Even carrying out a detailed snow profile and stability tests can only tell you what the conditions are on the spot. We experienced this last year when the SLF staff went on a trip together. We’d just drawn up a snow profile a few hundred metres before, and the snow cover seemed very stable. We skied on further into the valley and suddenly there was a loud ‘boom’. We all froze inwardly – but luckily, we were on the flat side of the mountain. It’s on a gradient of 30 degrees or more that things get risky.</div>
    <div>“I have been very lucky to be doing research in a field I’m already passionate about in my hobby time. I hope I’ll be able to stay in Davos for a long time, because I really like it here. And I’ve noticed how important it is to experience the place in all weathers, every day. That means I have a much better understanding of the snow cover. When I study a snow profile, for example, I might think: ah, that was yesterday’s rough winds. My wife is also an enthusiastic ski tourer. Sometimes she can’t wait to go on a ski tour on the weekend, whereas I would rather lie at home on the sofa”.</div>
  </article>
  <article id="a164" issue="120" name="“Emotions are not universal, but are determined by morals and socialisation”" lang="en">
    <div class="title">“Emotions are not universal, but are determined by morals and socialisation”</div>
    <div class="date">07/03/2019</div>
    <div class="author">Judith Hochstrasser</div>
    <div class="abstract">Fear is no longer linked to feelings of shame. On the contrary, we encourage children to talk about it. But disgust is even more laden with taboos than it used to be. The historian Bettina Hitzer explains in this interview how emotions have changed over time.
</div>
    <div>In the late 1960s, scientists first recognised that it’s emotions that actually make decision-making possible, says Bettina Hitzer, who runs the Minerva Research Focus ‘Emotions and Illness. Histories of an Intricate Relation’, a project of the Research Centre ‘History of Emotions’. | Photo: Saied Sharifi</div>
    <div>For the past ten years, the history of emotions – especially of the 18th, 19th and 20th centuries – has been a research topic at the Max Planck Institute for Human Development. The researchers there want to trace the societal norms that shape our emotions, and demonstrate how emotions have altered over the course of time. Bettina Hitzer runs the project ‘Emotions and Illness. Histories of an Intricate Relation’ and has been involved with the Institute’s emotion research right from the start.</div>
    <div>Bettina Hitzer, are people’s feelings different today from 100 years ago?</div>
    <div>Yes, I’m convinced of it, even though psychologists and neuroscientists like to argue that emotions are a universal constant. That might be true in terms of neural activity. But for me as a historian, emotions only exist when they are perceived by their subject. And this is where the cultural and historical context comes into play.</div>
    <div>How can an emotion change?</div>
    <div>People say that fear makes sense in evolutionary terms, because it warns us of danger. But then the objects of our fear change. In the late 19th century, for example, many people were afraid of being buried alive. Today, people tend to fear that brain death will be diagnosed and organs removed for transplantation, even though we might still be conscious in some way. This change has to do with technological developments. But the emotion of fear itself has also changed, because not only has the manner in which we evaluate it in moral terms changed, but so has the manner in which we talk about it. This, in turn, has an impact on the emotion itself.</div>
    <div>How is that?</div>
    <div>As educational guides from the late 19th century prove, the dominant opinion at the time was that a well-brought-up child with a good character would easily overcome certain fears – such as a fear of the dark – without needing much help. If this didn’t happen, then the child would be ashamed of it, and would do everything possible so as not to speak of it. But this could make his or her fears all the greater. Today, this stance has changed completely, at least in Western society. We even encourage children to speak about their fears. Fear is far less burdened by shame.</div>
    <div>We often read that parents used to grieve less on the death of a child in the Middle Ages or the Early Modern Period.</div>
    <div>There are in fact many sources that suggest the opposite, and that speak of great sadness on the part of parents. Nevertheless, this grief will have felt different from today, because it was more natural to experience the death of a child. And people were anchored in specific patterns of belief and thought that enabled the death of a child to be assessed more positively: as the passage of an innocent being now gone home to God. Probably only very few people share such a belief today. It’s almost impossible to answer questions about the intensity of emotions. Emotion history does not measure emotions quantitatively, but investigates qualitative aspects and shows how emotions change.</div>
    <div>So emotions themselves change. Have any emotions that used to be important been forgotten today? Or did emotions once exist that we now ignore?</div>
    <div>Yes – or at least emotions that remain very much in the background. Ute Frevert, who founded this research field, speaks of “lost and found emotions”. For example, empathy is an emotion that was only invented in more recent times. And in the early 20th century, people spoke far more openly about their feelings of disgust towards things or people. Today, however, disgust is laden with taboos.</div>
    <div>Are we too politically correct for this particular emotion?</div>
    <div>That’s going a bit too far. If we feel a sense of disgust towards other human beings, it’s regarded as an asocial emotion. This is why it’s often kept secret. But it reappears between the lines, as it were – in linguistic images, perhaps. For example, if homeless people are described in a certain way – such as scruffy and unkempt – then it’s clear to everyone that what’s meant is a feeling of disgust. In the first half of the 20th century, however, disgust was often expressed openly. In the 1920s, doctors didn’t want to put patients with advanced tumours in the ‘normal’ hospital wards, because their bodily disfigurements were regarded as nauseating. They wanted to get them out of hospital as quickly as possible, and often left their families to deal with the problem on their own. At the same time, people discussed relatively openly how they might reduce these feelings of disgust. Today, we rarely see such advanced tumours. With cancer of the mouth or jaw, disgust is still an issue. But doctors and nurses discuss this almost solely amongst themselves, because it’s not something they can really communicate in public.</div>
    <div>How much does science affect our emotions?</div>
    <div>When we look back at the last 150 years, we can see that science has been very important, especially in the fields of psychology, psychoanalysis and physiology. These sciences have developed models for how specific emotions function, and how we can deal with them better. Just think of the different varieties of psychotherapy, which explain and treat emotions in a very specific way.</div>
    <div>Was there ever a time in which the sciences greatly changed how we perceive emotions?</div>
    <div>In the cultural sciences, we use the concept of the ‘emotional turn’ to describe something that happened in society and the sciences in the 1980s. Its prime aspect was that emotions were no longer seen as being irrational or pathological. And as a more rational phenomenon, they became more accessible to the sciences. We can also criticise this rationalisation process for making emotions and cognition almost indistinguishable from each other. Initial approaches to treating emotions as a scientific object actually emerged in the late 1960s in cognitive psychology. People realised back then that emotions are actually what make decisions possible. These ideas later entered the realm of positive psychology and the concept of emotional intelligence.</div>
    <div>What did the ‘emotional turn’ change about society?</div>
    <div>The new social movements of the 1970s and ’80s, such as the women’s movement, the peace movement and the environmental movement, discovered that emotions can be a proof of authenticity. But in the public debates of the day, this also brought them into open confrontation with those whose arguments were characterised by cool rationality and were based on risk calculations or security policy. Emotions were presented as an alternative to a society that seemed to be philistine. One of the major demands made during the youth riots in Zurich in the 1980s was: ‘We want more warmth in this cold city!’.</div>
    <div>Meanwhile, much research is underway into emotions. Are the emotions of researchers also important in this?</div>
    <div>Yes. As a historian, I’ve been busy looking into the emotional history of cancer, and how it is determined by spatial constellations and technological apparatus. In the 1950s and ’60s, technological developments resulted in the sudden emergence of large-scale radiation equipment. Patients were placed in isolated rooms for this treatment, so it wasn’t easy to find out how they felt. That’s why I’ve been looking at photos of people in such situations and have been trying to imagine how I would feel if I had to lie in such an apparatus. What would my emotions be when this machine envelops me and the slab beneath me moves?</div>
    <div>How did this help you in your research?</div>
    <div>My emotional response to these images pointed me to certain details that I might otherwise have missed, and that I in fact later discovered in patient files. So my own emotions put me on a certain track, and helped me to become a better historian. And yet, in a second step, I had to reflect on my own emotions and ask myself how much they are actually determined by my own cultural context today.</div>
    <div>You’ve been involved with the research project ‘History of emotions’ right from the start. What discoveries have surprised you the most?</div>
    <div>At the beginning, I was sceptical about whether researching the history of emotions would go beyond scratching the surface. But in the course of my work, I have realised that it’s not just the so-called ‘ego documents’ that tell us about emotions – such as diaries or letters – but all kinds of sources, such as patient reports, court judgements, photos and so on, even if emotions are not explicitly mentioned. It’s both demanding and enlightening to be able to relate all these different sources to each other.</div>
    <div>I’ll close with a personal question: why are you interested in emotions?</div>
    <div>First, because it was a blank spot in historiography for a long time, and we’ve been able to understand history better since we started researching into emotions. Secondly, engaging with emotions has made it very clear to me that my spontaneous feelings are much more closely linked to my upbringing and my cultural context than I would have thought. Many emotions I used to regard as natural are not as universal as we think, but determined by our morals and our socialisation.</div>
  </article>
</corpus>